# Tom Ritchford

- http://github.com/rec
- tom.ritchford@gmail.com
- +31 64 121 2749
- Amsterdam, Netherlands

I specialize in rapid development of highly reliable, performant, scalable, minimal, clear and maintainable solutions to difficult problems.

Decades of experience! A plethora of projects taken from conception to completion, production, packaging and distribution.

Expert in Python and C++, solid in Java, C and JS, conversant in many others.

- backend
- search
- fintech: option modeling, ledgers, position management
- big data
- distributed systems
- · audio and DSP
- real-time control
- and more

## **Employment Highlights**

### Lead Programmer, SuperDuperDB (May 2023 -- Sep 2023)

https://github.com/SuperDuperDB/superduperdb

SuperDuperDB is not a database, but a Python system integrating existing databases with AI tools like vector search and LLMs.

I was tasked with making the working Python codebase "professional" so to be released to the public as a library, and this I did, by writing many pytest tests, adding practically complete typing enforced with mypy, refactoring and renaming and removing cruft, and of course writing reams of readable class, method and function documentation.

I wrote design documents, really my favorite part: for *structured logging*, *monitoring*, *and journaling* (a small but very useful API which allowed repeatable computation with fairly marginal extra effort); and for a *fully typed REST server* (including a tiny demo!) with an automatically generated OpenAPI specification.

# CTO, Engora (April 2021 -- Feb 2023)

Engora was an innovative search engine for mechanical engineering parts.

<sup>&</sup>quot;Everything should be made as simple as possible, but no simpler" -various

The founder created a good demo, and then raised money through crowdfunding. I came in some months after as CTO: I had my hands in everything, but here are the bits I wrote all of (Python, PostgreSQL, SqlAlchemy):

- A parts crawler over two dozen disparate sites and a million parts, carefully rate-limited, harvested directly, then proxied, finally using ScraperAPI's fancy new asynchronous proxy.
- A PostgreSQL parts database with key information from each parts page: I wrote a small database quickly, then rewrote it entirely four months later.
- A data store based on S3, using multiple providers, with an incremental offsite "physical" backup stream; and on top of that, a data resource management system, for convenient replication of projects containing multiple, reproducible resources, including PostgreSLQ databases, directories and sharded files.
- A neat little proprietary *memory-mapped index* for direct searching and retrieval, and Whoosh for text searching.
- A Flask web server (using nginx/gunicorn in production) and a couple of Dockers supporting all of these.
- Deployment, configuration files and variables, monitoring variables, logging, user interaction journaling, and other unsexy but satisfying details.
- Practically complete test coverage of almost everything
- And to run all of those, a tidy typer CLI named engora, with over two dozen commands and subcommands, hundreds of flags and "practically complete" documentation, used every day by almost everyone in the company.

#### Lead developer on BiblioPixel, Maniacal Labs (2016-2019)

Maniacal Lab's BiblioPixel was a popular lighting control program written in Python that controlled LEDs and smart bulbs in strips, matrices, cubes and other layouts.

I rewrote it from the ground up, adding a REST server for pixel and higher-level control, code and data plug-ins, many animators including video feedback with an IIR filter, and a new data model using numpy arrays, leading to very roughly a 30x speedup with perfect backwards compatibility.

Mostly Python, some Cython and C++. (I'd use pybind11 instead of Cython if I had to do it again.)

## Senior software engineer at Ripple (2014-2016)

Ripple is a financial technology firm with its own eponymous cryptocurrency. I worked on their flagship application rippled, the complex and complicated

C++17 crypto-ledger that implements their XRP cryptocurrency, on the ledger code, on deployment, debugging, devops, build and monitoring, mostly in C++ with some Python.

#### CTO, World Wide Woodshed (2009-2014)

I had always wanted to write a complete desktop audio application!

World Wide Woodshed's SlowGold was a leader in music practice software from the 1990s. I bought half the tiny company, and was the sole developer for a brand-new product in C++, with high-quality audio, subtle and intuitive editing tools, and little details like three second restart after shutdown.

We had many dedicated customers, but not enough to justify keeping in business, so we shut down, and open sourced the software in 2016.

### Software engineer, Google (2004-2009)

I joined Google New York when it was a single floor overlooking Times Square, worked on Google's first question-answering system, then their first Music Search, then its short-lived Real Estate search, all in C++.

This led me to GoogleBase, a database of tens of billions of items planned for millions of users. Leading a tiny and changing team, over two years we built a universal reporting and computation framework in Python that I had proposed and designed: it was still in common use years later.

As a reward for this slog, I was privileged to work on GWS, the front end program, written in C++ that generated all Google results pages, for i18n, l10n and translations, and the GWS live experiment framework.

And I interviewed hundreds of engineers, traveling twice to Korea and once to Hungary for this.

I used C++, Java and Python, and the usual string of Google technologies.

## Senior software developer, Netomat (2001-2004)

Netomat had an innovative rich media tool to let users and advertisers create and send Netomat "experiences" – little Java applets (it seemed more reasonable at the time) minisites with animation, sound and internal navigation - to users who could edit them within the email itself.

I designed and wrote the animation engine and front-end, most of the animation types and the manual.

Still one of my favorite "neat hacks" ever, I wrote a tool that converted "experiences" right into Java bytecode, for a 40-80% savings in download and memory size.

## Skills

- Architecture and high-level design: clean, simple, practical, scale-appropriate, 12-factor
- Brutal, thorough testing and CI
- Python: Flask/SQLAlchemy/Django/FastAPI/Pydantic, numpy, Cython, real-time, packaging, typing!, and more...
- C/C++: modern C++11-23, STL/template programming, Boost, concurrency, DSP, Juce, real-time
- Java: distributed systems, i18n/110n
- Considerable Javascript, strong Linux, Bash scripting
- Data analysis and retrieval: clustering, search and indexing, data pipelines,
  S3, MapReduce, log analysis
- PostgreSQL database design, use and some admin
- Strong Git (I wrote this: https://github.com/rec/gitz)
- Practical DevOps: sysadmin "classic", deployment/release/integration, monitoring and logging
- Globalization: Internationalization, localization, translation, Unicode and encodings
- Performance optimization
- Fintech: ledger systems, option models
- Real-time systems: digital audio and DSP, lighting control systems, MIDI
- Tool building: see my tools dashboard at https://github.com/rec
- $\bullet$ .en:N .fr:C1 .nl:B2 .de:B1 .id:A2 .es:A2

## Education

I have a B.Sc. with First Class Honours in Mathematics from Carleton University, Canada.